{
  "exams": [
    {
      "date": "January 31st, 2025",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Your firm operates in a Modigliani-Miller world, and it is undertaking its first, and only investment right now. This investment costs 1 million EUR and is financed with 800,000 EUR new equity, and 200,000 EUR new debt. This money is used to undertake a project with positive NPV, equal to 50,000 EUR. Which of the following statements is true (only one statement is true):",
          "options": {
            "a": "The market value of your firm' total assets increases by 50,000 EUR",
            "b": "The market value of your firm' total liabilities (=equity + debt) increases by 50,000 EUR",
            "c": "The market value of your firm' total assets increases more than the market value of your firm' total liabilities",
            "d": "The market value of your firm' total assets increases by 1,050,000 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "Consider the Market-Value Balance Sheet. The total value of assets (and of equity + debt, i.e. total liabilities) increases by the present value of the new investment, i.e. its investment cost (1 mln EUR) + NPV."
        },
        {
          "question": "One of the following assumptions is necessary to ensure that Modigliani-Miller Proposition 1 holds, even if the debt in the capital structure of the firm is risky. Which one? (only one possibility is correct)",
          "options": {
            "a": "The capital structure of the firm affects the choice of the future projects undertaken by the firm",
            "b": "The default of the firm produces indirect costs, such as fire sales of the firm assets",
            "c": "The capital structure of the firm does not affect the choice of the future projects undertaken by the firm",
            "d": "Firms can borrow money at an interest rate which is lower than the interest rate paid by individuals borrowing money"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "MM Proposition 1 holds under several assumptions, i.e. that capital markets are perfectly competitive and have no frictions (which implies that all agents can borrow money at the same rates, excluding answer d.), when there are no arbitrage opportunities and when the firm financing decisions do not change the cash-flows generated by its investment. This is the case when the capital structure of the firm does not affect the choice of projects implemented by the firm (answer c). Answer b is wrong because in the MM-world firm default does not have any cost (direct or indirect)."
        },
        {
          "question": "It is correctly believed that if debtholders fully anticipate the possibility of debt overhang, then the cost of this distortion is entirely suffered by shareholders. What is the reason for this? (only one statement is correct)",
          "options": {
            "a": "The reason is that, if debtholders fully anticipate the potential debt overhang, they know that firms with high levels of debt undertake only safe and efficient projects",
            "b": "The reason is that, if debtholders fully anticipate the potential debt overhang, they require a high return in order to finance the firm, and this in the end reduces the return earned by shareholders",
            "c": "The reason is that, if debtholders fully anticipate the potential debt overhang, they know that firms with low levels of debt undertake only safe and efficient projects",
            "d": "The reason is that, if debtholders fully anticipate the potential debt overhang, they know that all firms are never able to undertake new projects"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "A firm is hit by debt overhang if its current level of debt (i.e. its leverage) is so high that for the firm shareholders is not profitable anymore to undertake efficient projects (i.e. projects with a positive NPV). Therefore, only firms with high level of debt can suffer debt overhang (so, c. is wrong), and a. is also wrong because debt overhang causes exactly the opposite, the impossibility to undertake efficient projects. Finally, d. is also wrong because only firms hit by debt overhang (i.e. firm with high leverage) may not be able to invest in new, efficient projects (the fact that they cannot invest in new inefficient project is actually a good news). Only b. then is correct."
        },
        {
          "question": "You are the unique owner of a company, and you are protected by limited liability. Your company is facing a situation of financial distress. Your company has debt with face value 6 mln EUR due in exactly two years, i.e. at time t=2. No interests are paid before that maturity, nor are due at maturity. If you pursue your traditional business strategy, the total market value of your firm in exactly two years will be equal to 5.5 mln EUR (for sure) and therefore your company will default on its debt and go bankrupt. If you decide to undertake an innovative, risky business strategy, the value of your company in exactly two years will be either 10 million (an event with probability 40%) or 2 mln EUR (an event with probability 60%). Which of the following statements is true? (only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "For you it is profitable to undertake the innovative, risky strategy. However, this strategy expropriates the debtholders, who are going to suffer an expected loss of 1.9 mln EUR on their credit",
            "b": "For you it is profitable to undertake the innovative, risky strategy. However, this strategy expropriates the debtholders, who are going to suffer an expected loss of 3.5 mln EUR on their credit",
            "c": "For you it is profitable to undertake the innovative, risky strategy. This increases the expected value of your company and therefore also debtholders earn from this choice",
            "d": "For you it is profitable to continue pursuing the traditional business strategy"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "Let us compute the payoff for you (=only equity holder) and debtholders when pursuing the two strategies. Traditional strategy: value of the firm at t=2 (in exactly two years) equals 5.5 mln EUR. Firm defaults, you earn zero, debtholders earn 5.5 mln EUR (remember: you are protected by limited liability, so the debtholders can obtain only all the firm value, whenever this is lower than their credit towards the firm). Innovative, risky strategy: if successful, firm value at t=2 equals 10 mln, so debtholders get repaid fully (=6 mln) and you earn the residual (10-6 = 4 mln). If failure, firm value at t=2 equals 2 mln, firm defaults, debtholders obtain the 2 mln, you earn zero. In expected terms, with this strategy you earn (0.4)*4 + (0.6)*0 = 1.6 mln, so it is better than the traditional strategy. Debtholders earn in expected terms (0.4)*6+(0.6)*2=3.6 mln, which is lower than the 5.5. mln they obtain if you were pursuing the traditional strategy. In expected terms, the fact that you chose the risky strategy costs them 5.5-3.6 = 1.9 mln EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "You buy today 20 European call options on Tesla stocks expiring in exactly one month, each with strike price 400 EUR. You pay each call option 30 EUR. Assume you finance the entire cost of purchasing the options by borrowing money at 0.25% interest per month. Assume the Tesla stock price at expiration is equal to S > 400, where S is random variable whose value in one month is unknown today. Compute the stock price S at which this portfolio of call options provides a zero payoff at the options expiration date. (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "401.75 EUR",
            "b": "415.025 EUR",
            "c": "425.055 EUR",
            "d": "430.075 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "The portfolio payoff in one year equals (20 times) the call option payoff at expiration (i.e. at the exercise date), minus the amount owed on the loan of 20*30 = 600 EUR, necessary to buy the call todays: 20 × (max{S – 400; 0}) – 600 * 1.0025 = 20 × (S – 400) – 601.5. The payoff at expiration equals zero if: 20(S-400) – 601.5 = 0. The price S at which you earn a zero payoff is S = 430.075."
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of the following statement is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "In the Modigliani-Miller world an open market share repurchase has no effect on the stock price, which is higher than the cum-dividend price if a dividend were paid instead",
            "b": "In the Modigliani-Miller world an open market share repurchase has no effect on the stock price, which equals the ex-dividend price if a dividend were paid instead",
            "c": "In the Modigliani-Miller world an open market share repurchase has no effect on the stock price, which equals the cum-dividend price if a dividend were paid instead",
            "d": "None of the above is true"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "See the lecture on payout policy, the example with Genron where Share Repurchase and dividend payments are compared."
        },
        {
          "question": "The price of PFIZER stock today is 25.6 EUR. On the financial market you can trade a call option on PFIZER stock that expires in six months, with strike price 27 EUR. According to the average market's expectations the price of one PFIZER stock in six months is going to be either 28 EUR (with probability equal to 0 < p < 1) or 24 EUR (with probability 1-p). The risk-free interest rate on the market is equal to zero. What is the price of the call option now? To price the option use the replicating portfolio method.",
          "options": {
            "a": "0.1 EUR",
            "b": "0.4 EUR",
            "c": "1.2 EUR",
            "d": "2.1 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "The option payoffs at expiration are 28-27 EUR in case PFIZER's stock price increases to 28 EUR, and 0 in case it decreases to 24 EUR (the call then is out of the money at expiration). Solving for the replicating portfolio gives Delta = ¼ and B = -6. Therefore, the call price today is (1/4)*25.6 - 6 = 0.4 EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "What financial position has more downside exposure at the expiration date of the option, considering only the expiration payoff:",
          "options": {
            "a": "A long position on a call",
            "b": "A long position on a put",
            "c": "A short position on a call",
            "d": "A short position on a put"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "The downside exposure refers to the maximum amount of money you can lose if you trade in the financial security, here a call or a put option. As it is stated in the question, this downside exposure has to be computed at the expiration date of the option. Therefore, consider the payoff you obtain at expiration if you are a. long of a call (=you have one call in your portfolio), or b. long of one put, or c. short of a call (=you sold one call and did not buy any security to “cover” this position), or d. short of a put. These payoffs depend on the realized stock price at expiration for the underlying stock. Given that being long in one option you cannot lose money at expiration considering only the expiration payoff, only the short positions can give you a loss. This loss is bounded at - K for the put, while it can be of any amount for the call."
        },
        {
          "question": "You are a specialist in leveraged buyouts (LBOs) and your analysts tell you that there is an interesting acquisition possible, the company CZC Inc. that is publicly traded. At this moment, CZC's stock price is 12 USD, and there are 10 million shares outstanding. CZC has no debt and your analysts believe is currently managed inefficiently. They believe that by replacing the current management of CZC you could increase the value of the company by 20%. You decide then to issue a tender offer for 50% of the outstanding shares of CZC, in order to take control. You offer 14 USD per share and you plan to pay the entire tender offer with new debt. Once you take control of CZC, you will charge the entire debt necessary to pay for the tender offer on the CZC balance sheet. Suppose your tender offer is successful. What is the value of your stake in CZC after you take control of the company and implement the predicted value increase?",
          "options": {
            "a": "37 mln USD",
            "b": "74 mln USD",
            "c": "12 mln USD",
            "d": "24 mln USD"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "The current market value of CZC is 120 mln USD (=12 USD times 10 mln shares), which corresponds to the total market value of CZC equity, because the company has no debt. After the takeover and the replacement of the management team, CZC total value increases by 20%, and is equal to 144 mln USD then. Notice that CZC will now have debt in its capital structure, because it is charged the debt used to pay for the tender offer. Given that you offer 14 USD per share and you buy 5 mln shares (exactly 50% of the 10 mln existing shares), the tender offer costs 70 mln USD. The value of CZC' equity after the takeover then is 144 – 70 = 74 mln USD. The value of your stake in CZC (50% of the equity) is then 74/2 = 37 mln USD."
        },
        {
          "question": "According to the Q-theory of investment, Tobin's Q can predict under which conditions firm invest and/or take over other firms. Which of the following statements is true, according to this theory? (only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "If the unit price of bundled capital, q, is higher than the unit price of unbundled capital (=1), then firms acquire new capital by purchasing other firms' assets when Q is smaller than q",
            "b": "If the unit price of bundled capital, q, is higher than the unit price of unbundled capital (=1), then firms acquire new capital by purchasing other firms' assets when Q is larger than one but smaller than q",
            "c": "If the unit price of bundled capital, q, is lower than the unit price of unbundled capital (=1), then firms acquire new capital by purchasing other firms' assets when Q is smaller than q",
            "d": "If the unit price of bundled capital, q, is lower than the unit price of unbundled capital (=1), then firms acquire new capital by purchasing other firms' assets when Q is larger than q"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "Q is the shadow value of capital, and it represents the market value of a unit of capital (i.e. the Tobin Q per unit of capital that costs 1 to be replaced). The firm acquires assets by taking over other firms when Q<q = the unit cost of bundled capital, irrespectively of the relation between q and 1. For sure, if q<1, and Q>q then the firm acquires new assets acquiring bundled capital."
        },
        {
          "question": "According to some authors, efficient capital markets can discipline corporate management because poor managerial decisions are punished by shareholders, who sell their shares making an hostile takeover more attractive to other management teams who believe that they can run the company more efficiently. Which of the following statement describes a problem that could invalidate the previous idea? (only one statement gives you the right answer)",
          "options": {
            "a": "If the current management takes poor managerial decisions then the cost of capital for the corporation increases",
            "b": "If the current management takes poor managerial decisions but target shareholders anticipate the value creation due to the change in control, then if they own a very small stake in the target firm they may have no incentive to sell their shares",
            "c": "If the current management takes poor managerial decisions then this means that it pursues its own goals",
            "d": "If the current management takes poor managerial decisions then the firm goes bankruptcy for sure"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "Statement a is correct, but it is not related to the mechanism described in the question. Statement b might be correct or wrong, but in any case is also not related to the mechanism described (it can be wrong because the management could take poor decisions even if it pursues shareholders' goals, i.e. the maximization of shareholders' value). Statement d is simply wrong: bad decisions not always lead to bankruptcy necessarily."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "date": "January 31st, 2023",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Consider a financial market without frictions in which all the assumptions of the Modigliani-Miller paradigm are satisfied. ChatBot Corporation currently holds 10 million EUR in cash and has no debt. Its assets-in-place are expected to generate free cash flows of 20 million per year, starting from next year, forever. Currently, there are 10 million ChatBot shares outstanding. ChatBot's cost of capital is 10%. The company is planning to use the 10 million EUR cash to repurchase shares on the open market. Which of the following sentences is correct?",
          "options": {
            "a": "The total market value of ChatBot before the share repurchase takes place is 200 mln EUR, and its share price is 20 EUR. If the company repurchases shares, it can buy 500000 shares on the open market, and the share price after the repurchase still equals 20 EUR.",
            "b": "The total market value of ChatBot before the share repurchase takes place is 200 mln EUR, and its share price is 20 EUR. If the company repurchases shares, it can buy 476190 shares on the open market, and the share price after the repurchase is 21 EUR.",
            "c": "The total market value of ChatBot before the share repurchase takes place is 210 mln EUR, and its share price is 21 EUR. If the company repurchases shares, it can buy 500000 shares on the open market, and the share price after the repurchase is 21 EUR.",
            "d": "The total market value of ChatBot before the share repurchase takes place is 210 mln EUR, and its share price is 21 EUR. If the company repurchases shares, it can buy 476190 shares on the open market, and the share price after the repurchase is 21 EUR."
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "The market value of ChatBot is the sum of the present value of its future cash-flows, a perpetuity of C=20 mln per year discounted at the cost of capital, r=10%, (20 mln / 0.10 = 200 mln) plus the 10 mln cash = 210 mln EUR. The current share price, i.e. the price before the share repurchase takes place, therefore is 210 mln / 10 mln (number of share outstanding) = 21 EUR. If the company repurchases shares by using the 10 mln EUR cash, it can buy (10,000,000 / 21) = 476190 shares. After the repurchase, there are only 10,000,000 – 476,190 = 9,523,810 shares left. The share price after the repurchase is then equal to 200 mln / 9523810 = 21 EUR. Actually, you do not need to check that the share price after repurchase equals the price before the repurchase, this is always the case in a Modligliani-Miller world."
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose we are living in a Modigliani-Miller world with frictionless capital markets. One newly established firm has no assets-in-place, and its activity consists only in the investment in a new project. This new project costs I mln EUR, and has a positive NPV. This new investment is financed half by new equity, and half by new debt, which is riskless and pays an interest rate equal to the risk-free rate offered on the financial markets. Before this new investment, the firm had no equity and no debt outstanding. After this investment, the market value of the firm equity:",
          "options": {
            "a": "Equals I mln EUR",
            "b": "Equals 0.5I mln EUR",
            "c": "Is higher than 0.5I mln EUR",
            "d": "Equals the market value of firm debt."
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "Consider the market value balance sheet of this firm after the new project has been undertaken. The total value of assets (that was equal to zero before the investment) equals the Present Value of the new project, i.e. I + NPV. Before the investment, both the value of equity and the value of debt were equal to zero. After the project is implemented, the value of debt is 0.5I because the debt is risk-free and financed at the risk-free interest rate, therefore its value today equals its face value (=0.5I because it is stated that half of the new investment was financed with new debt). In order to equalize the value of liabilities (Equity + Debt) to the total value of assets, we need that the market value of Equity is 0.5I + NPV > 0.5I, because NPV is positive."
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "In the Modigliani-Miller world the cost of capital of a corporation depends on its capital structure",
            "b": "In the Modigliani-Miller world the cost of capital of a corporation does not depend on its capital structure",
            "c": "In the Modigliani-Miller world the cost of equity capital of a corporation does not depend on its capital structure",
            "d": "In the Modigliani-Miller world the cost of debt capital of a corporation is always equal to the cost of equity capital."
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "b is the exact statement of MM proposition 2. c is wrong because, again by MM2, the cost of equity capital increases with leverage, while d is wrong because the cost of equity capital is higher than the cost of debt capital whenever equity is riskier than debt."
        },
        {
          "question": "Debt overhang is typically considered of concern because it stops highly levered firms to undertake efficient projects. Which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "If pre-existing debtholders fully anticipate the possible future debt overhang, then they suffer entirely its cost, by paying a higher interest rate",
            "b": "If pre-existing debtholders fully anticipate the possible future debt overhang, then they ask the company to pay a lower return on debt they have bought",
            "c": "If pre-existing debtholders fully anticipate the possible future debt overhang, then its cost is suffered entirely by equity holders",
            "d": "If pre-existing debtholders fully anticipate the possible future debt overhang, then the debt is fully reimbursed before maturity."
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "Fully anticipating debt overhang means that the existing debtholders anticipate the firm is not going to invest in future, efficient projects, and by doing so it increases the riskiness of the pre-existing debt. When they realize this, they understand that the riskiness of their debt is high, due to the fact that, if future good investment opportunities arise, the firm will not take them. Therefore, the debt holders ask for a higher interest rate on the debt, or even refuse to lend. The cost of debt overhang then goes to the firm equity holders, who will not be able to invest in this new, efficient projects. a does not make sense, since debtholders do not pay an interest, they receive it. d is wrong because, unless stated otherwise, debtholders cannot ask for immediate reimbursement of the debt, they have to wait for its maturity. B is also wrong because if debtholders understand the debt may be riskier than what they thought (because of overhang), they will not require the company to pay a lower interest rate, but a higher one."
        },
        {
          "question": "A firm currently (at t = 0) has 1 unit of cash. The firm can either pay this cash out as a dividend now or retain the cash until next year (t = 1), when an investment opportunity arises with probability 1/2. The characteristics of the investment opportunity are the following. It costs 1 unit of cash. If undertaken, it increases firm profits by 0.1 < q < 1 units of cash every year forever, starting from year t = 1. The firm opportunity cost of capital is r(wacc) = 10%, and the firm has no debt. Current firm shareholders want to cash in any capital gain they make next year, if any (which is the case if the firm retains cash, the project opportunity arises at t=1, and the firm invests in it at t=1). In this case, the shareholders will cash in only the capital gain. Shareholders are risk-neutral and the risk-free interest rate equals zero. Dividends are taxed at 20% rate, there is no corporate tax, and there are no taxes on capital gains, nor personal or income taxes. Which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "If q = 0.3 units (of cash) then the firm shareholders prefer that the firm retains the cash until next year rather than paying dividends now",
            "b": "If q = 0.1 units (of cash) then the firm shareholders prefer that the firm retains the cash until next year rather than paying dividends now",
            "c": "If q = 0.3 units (of cash) then the firm shareholders prefer that the firm pays dividends now rather than retaining the cash until next year",
            "d": "If q = 0.05 units (of cash) then the firm shareholders prefer that the firm retains the cash until next year rather than paying dividends now"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "If the firm pays out the unit of cash as dividends at t=0, shareholders earn 1(1-0.20) = 0.8 units of cash, net of taxes on dividends. If the firm retains the cash, next year (t=1) it can invest it in the project. If such a project exists, its NPV at t=1 equals q/0.10 - 1 = 10q - 1 units of cash since it pays a perpetuity of q, discounted at the cost of capital (10%), which represents a capital gain (which is not taxed). The shareholders then expect to cash in a capital gain worth 10q - 1 units at t=1 if the firm retains the unit of cash and invests. Given that the shareholders are risk-neutral and that the risk-free rate is zero, if the firm retains cash and invests the PV of the capital gain at t=0 equals 10q – 1. Given that the investment opportunity arises with probability 1/2, the value of q that makes shareholders indifferent between receiving dividends now and the firm retaining cash solves (1/2)*(10q-1)= 0.8, i.e. q = 0.260. For any q higher than 0.260 the shareholders prefer that the firm retains cash rather than paying dividends now. NB: in an older solution, it was (wrongly) considered that the capital gain would be 10q. If you (wrongly) consider this case, then the q that makes shareholders indifferent between the two options is q = 0.160, and also in this case the only correct answer is a."
        },
        {
          "question": "An investor who sells a put option (= writer of the put) takes the opposite side of the contract from the investor who buys and holds the same put option (= the holder of the put). Which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "The writer of the put has the contractual obligation to sell the underlying stock at the put strike price K when the option expiration date is reached, if the holder of the put exercises it",
            "b": "The writer of the put has the contractual obligation to buy the underlying stock at the put strike price K when the option expiration date is reached, if the holder of the put exercises it",
            "c": "The writer of the put has the contractual obligation to buy the underlying stock at its price on the market when the option expiration date is reached, if the holder of the put exercises it",
            "d": "None of the above"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "a is wrong because the buyer (holder) of the put, by exercising the option, can sell the underlying stock at the strike price K to the investor who sold the option, who therefore has to buy it at K. c is wrong because the put seller has the obligation to buy the underlying stock at K, not at the market price at the expiration date."
        },
        {
          "question": "Consider two options, a call and a put, written on the same underlying stock. The two options expire at the same future date and have the same strike price K. Consider also a riskless bond with face value K, which matures (= is reimbursed) exactly at the options' exercise date. Which of the following sentences is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "Whether today (i) you buy the stock and the call, or (ii) you buy the bond and the put, in both cases you earn exactly the same payoff at the options' exercise date",
            "b": "Whether today (i) you buy the stock and the bond, or (ii) you buy the call and the put, in both cases you earn exactly the same payoff at the options' exercise date",
            "c": "Whether today (i) you buy the bond and the call, or (ii) you buy the bond and the put, in both cases you earn exactly the same payoff at the options' exercise date",
            "d": "Whether today (i) you buy the stock and the put, or (ii) you buy the bond and the call, in both cases you earn exactly the same payoff at the options' exercise date"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "See the graphs “Hedging a long position on a stock”. Buying the stock and the put gives the same payoff at expiration date as buying the bond and the call. This is also the premise for the put-call parity relation."
        },
        {
          "question": "The price of a given stock today is 25 EUR. There is a call option on this stock expiring in one year, with strike price of 27 EUR. According to the average market's expectations, the price of the stock in one year is going to be either 30 EUR, or 24 EUR. The risk-free interest rate equals zero. By using the replicating portfolio method, what is the value of the call option today?",
          "options": {
            "a": "0.5 EUR",
            "b": "1 EUR",
            "c": "1.5 EUR",
            "d": "2 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "If the stock price in one year equals 30 EUR, the call will be in-the-money, and its payoff at expiration will be equal to 30-27 = 3 EUR. If the stock price in one year equals 24 EUR, the call will be out-of-the-money, paying a payoff of zero. The replicating portfolio (D, B) then solves the system of equations: 30D + B = 3; 24D + B = 0. Which gives D = ½ and B = -12. By no arbitrage, the value of the call today equals the value of the portfolio today, which in turn equals (1/2)*25 − 12 = 12.5 – 12 = 0.5, because the replicating bond is riskless and pays a zero interest rate, while the price of the stock today is 25 EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "You are a risk-averse investor evaluating the option to abandon a project in one year, if some milestones results are not reached. The project embeds some systematic risk, i.e. risk that cannot be diversified. Which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "Your evaluation of the option to abandon the project is the same as the evaluation of a risk-neutral investor",
            "b": "Your evaluation of the option to abandon the project is higher than the evaluation of a risk-neutral investor",
            "c": "Your evaluation of the option to abandon the project is lower than the evaluation of a risk-neutral investor",
            "d": "None of the above"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "You actually abandon the project ( = exercise the option) if in one year you find out that you would make a loss by investing in this project. Therefore, the option to abandon reduces the volatility of the project future payoffs. You evaluate a lower volatility only if you are risk-averse, not when you are risk-neutral, and therefore you evaluate the option to abandon more when you are risk-averse than if you are risk-neutral."
        },
        {
          "question": "You are an LBO artist. You are thinking of setting up a holding company BOX Co., endowed with 30 mln EUR cash and to buy out company AAA Inc., whose total value of assets currently equals 200 mln EUR. AAA has 50 mln EUR of outstanding debt and 1 million shares outstanding. Your plan is to borrow the amount of money necessary to make a tender offer for 50% of the shares of AAA. In this tender offer, you offer to pay each AAA share its current market price (= the market price of the AAA share right before the announcement of a tender offer, assuming there is no leakage of information). If your tender offer is successful, you buy exactly the 50% of AAA outstanding shares, take control of the company and then merge it with BOX to create a new company, ABBA Inc. You will charge the new debt which was used to pay the tender offer of AAA on the balance sheet of the new company, ABBA Inc. Through the restructuring of ABBA Inc. you expect to be able to generate 50 mln EUR of extra value on the assets of this new company. The value of one share of ABBA after you have taken control of AAA, merged it with BOX, and restructured ABBA is closest to:",
          "options": {
            "a": "155 EUR",
            "b": "165 EUR",
            "c": "170 EUR",
            "d": "175 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "The total value of AAA assets before the operation is 200 mln EUR, of which existing debt is worth 50 mln, so total value of equity is 150 mln. Given that there is 1 million shares outstanding, before the LBO the share price of AAA is equal to 150 EUR. In order to buy 50% of AAA' shares (=500,000 shares) at the market price before the tender offer announcement (150 EUR), you need to borrow 500,000*150 EUR = 75 mln EUR (you can reach the same result by noticing that you need to pay 50% of 150 mln, the total value of equity of AAA). This additional 75 mln EUR debt will be on the balance sheet of the new company ABBA you create by merging AAA with BOX. Total value of ABBA (after restructuring) = 200 mln (from AAA) + 30 mln (from BOX) + 50 mln (from restructuring) = 280 mln. Total value of ABBA debt = 50 mln (from AAA) + 75 mln (necessary for the takeover) = 125 mln. Therefore, total value of ABBA equity = 280 – 125 = 155 mln. Share price = 155 EUR (because there is still 1 million shares outstanding, and the total value of equity is 155 mln EUR)."
        },
        {
          "question": "According to the “stakeholders perspective\", the managers' mission should be to maximize the total stakeholders' welfare, and not the total shareholders' value. Why is it difficult in practice to maximize the total stakeholders' welfare?",
          "options": {
            "a": "Because we can exactly quantify only the total welfare of employees of a given company",
            "b": "Because we can exactly quantify the total employees' welfare, but we cannot sum it to shareholders' value",
            "c": "Because corporate governance mission is to maximize the total shareholders' value",
            "d": "Because there is no reliable market measure of stakeholders' welfare"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "A is wrong because we cannot exactly quantify the employees' welfare. B is wrong for the same reason as a. c is wrong because it defines the “shareholders perspective” of Corporate Governance, and it is not relevant."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "date": "June 20th, 2023",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "According to prospect theory, in a decision problem under uncertainty the framing of contingencies matter. In particular, several experiments show that people behave according to the so called \"Allais paradox\". This paradox refers to the fact that, when an individual solves an economic problem under uncertainty:",
          "options": {
            "a": "When making its choice, the individual maximizes its expected utility",
            "b": "A change in the probability of outcomes has less impact on the individual's choice when the initial outcome is certain",
            "c": "A change in the probability of outcomes has more impact on the individual's choice when the initial outcome is certain",
            "d": "A change in the probability of outcomes affects the reference point of the individual in the decision problem"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "See slide “Framing of contingencies” in the Behavioral Finance lecture. b is simply the opposite of c, and therefore is clearly wrong. d is wrong because the certainty affect does not refer in any sense to the existence of a “reference point” in the individual's choice. a is obviously wrong according to the whole behavioral approach."
        },
        {
          "question": "In June 13, 2016, MMM announced its acquisition of LLL, offering $196 for each LLL share. The market price of one LLL share just before the announcement was $131.08, and it jumped to $192.21 upon the announcement. Compute the merger spread. Suppose that sometime after announcement comes a public news that makes the merger deal less likely. Generally, we expect the merger spread to decrease or to increase after this public news?",
          "options": {
            "a": "Merger Spread = $64.92; after the news the merger spread is expected to increase",
            "b": "Merger Spread = $64.92; after the news the merger spread is expected to decrease",
            "c": "Merger Spread = $3.79; after the news the merger spread is expected to increase",
            "d": "Merger Spread = $3.79; after the news the merger spread is expected to decrease"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "Merger Spread= Offered Price-Price upon announcement = 196 - 192.21 = 3.79$. When the probability that the deal actually takes place lowers, the merger spread increases."
        },
        {
          "question": "The gross value of a project without considering its flexibility is the following. Currently (t = 0) its value is 1.45M EUR, while in one year (t=1) it can be 2M EUR, if the market expands, or 0.9M EUR, if the market contracts. At t=0 the investment in the project costs 1M EUR. However, you have the option to wait for one year and undertake the project at t=1. If you wait and invest at t=1 you do not earn any cash-flow at t=0, and the cost of the project raises to 1.2M EUR. You are risk-neutral, and the risk-free interest rate is equal to zero. The value at t=0 of the option to wait and invest in the project at t=1 is closest to:",
          "options": {
            "a": "0.14 M EUR",
            "b": "0.40 M EUR",
            "c": "0.75 M EUR",
            "d": "0.25 M EUR"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "The option to wait and to invest in one year is equivalent to a financial call option that expires at t=1, with K = 1.2M EUR (=the cost of the project if you invest next year, at t=1). At t=1 the underlying project may be worth 2M EUR, and in that case the option to invest will be in-the-money and you will exercise it, or it might be valued 0.9M EUR (in this case, the option to invest will be out-of-the-money, because 0.9M <1.2M, and you will not invest). Given that the problem does not give you the probabilities of these two events, you need to find the value of the (call) option to wait with the replicating portfolio method. Let the replicating portfolio be (S, B): by buying S units of the project and B riskless bonds (that pay a zero interest rate) today, you can replicate the payoffs of the call in any t=1 contingency. The replication portfolio is such that: 2*S + B = (2-1.2)M= 0.8M; 0.9S + B = 0. Solving this system of two equations gives you S = 0.73 and B = – 0.6545. The value of the (call) option to wait and invest next year equals the value of this portfolio today: 0.73(1.45) – 0.6545 = 0.40M EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "Assume we are in a Modigliani-Miller world without any frictions. Genron Corporation has 20 million in excess cash and has no debt. Starting next year, the firm expects to generate free cash flows of 48 million per year, forever. It has 10 million shares outstanding. Genron decides to use the 20 million excess cash to repurchase shares on the open market. After the share repurchase Genron plans to distribute its annual free cash flows as dividends. Genron's cost of capital is 12%. Compute the price of Genron share before and after the share repurchase.",
          "options": {
            "a": "Genron share price before repurchase = $4.8; share price after repurchase = $4.8",
            "b": "Genron share price before repurchase = $48 ; share price after repurchase = $48",
            "c": "Genron share price before repurchase = $42; share price after repurchase = $48",
            "d": "Genron share price before repurchase = $42; share price after repurchase = $42"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "Before Repurchase: Genron has $20M cash and also productive assets that will provide perpetual free cash flows of $48M per year. The market value of these assets is therefore; 48/0.12 = $400M. Thus, total firm value is then, V_0 =20+400=$420M. Since, there is no debt, the price per share P_0 =420M/10M = $42. After Repurchase: The firm can repurchase share = n = $20M/$42= 0.476M outstanding share. Therefore, the number of shares left on the market = 10 --.476 = 9.524M. The Market value of Firms assets is unchanged with respect to the situation before the repurchase (we are in MM world), except that the firm has paid 20M cash to buy the shares. Therefore, the total firm value equals $420M – $20M = $400M (or, alternatively, V = 48M/0.12 = 400M). The price per share after repurchase then is = 400/9.524 = $42."
        },
        {
          "question": "Consider a firm with risky debt in the Modigliani-Miller world. If the debtholders correctly anticipate the firm probability of default and evaluate its debt accordingly, then:",
          "options": {
            "a": "The cost of debt for the firm depends on the probability of default, while its cost of equity is independent of the capital structure of the firm",
            "b": "The cost of debt for the firm is independent of the probability of default, while its weighted average cost of capital depends on the capital structure of the firm",
            "c": "The cost of debt for the firm depends on the probability of default, while its weighted average cost of capital is independent of the capital structure of the firm",
            "d": "Both the firm cost of equity and its weighted average cost of capital increase with the probability that the firm defaults"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "See \"Cost of capital with risky debt in the MM world” in lecture 1."
        },
        {
          "question": "Some corporate governance scholars advocate the protection of shareholders' interest rather than the protection of the interests of stakeholders. Which of the following statement illustrates their argument correctly?",
          "options": {
            "a": "Shareholders, in particular minority shareholders, represent the constituency that is the least protected by contractual rights. The interests of other stakeholders, such as creditors and employees, have strong legal protection from creditors' legal rights and labor laws",
            "b": "Stakeholders represent the constituency that is the least protected by contractual rights. The interests of shareholders, both majority and minority ones, are already effectively protected by the Board of Directors",
            "c": "Stakeholders, in particular the firm employees, represent the constituency that is the least protected by contractual rights. The interests of shareholders, both majority and minority ones, are already effectively protected by the company CEO.",
            "d": "None of the above is true."
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "See Exercise 2 in the set of Corporate Governance Exercises (and see the lecture slides on the Lecture “Corporate Governance: an Introduction”)."
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose that interest rates are very low, also on risky debt. Then, companies can borrow money at a very low rate and suppose they invest the funds they have raised in corporate takeovers, for example in Leveraged Buyouts (LBOs). Under which of the conditions described below do you think that it is efficient for public firms to use anti-takeover provisions?",
          "options": {
            "a": "If the relative abundant capital is likely to increase the proportion of takeovers that are due to synergy creation",
            "b": "If the relative abundant capital is likely to increase the proportion of takeovers that are due to agency reasons",
            "c": "If the relative abundant capital increases the likelihood that takeovers are challenged by the Board of Directors",
            "d": "None of the above is true."
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "See Exercise 9 in the set of Exercises on “Market for corporate control”."
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose you want to buy one call option on TESLA stock. The option expires exactly in one year. The strike price of the call is $275, and the current price of TESLA stock is $255. The risk-free rate is 4.25% and the current price of a put option on TESLA stock that expires in one year and has the same strike price as the call is $12.34. Using the put-call parity, the price of the call is closest to?",
          "options": {
            "a": "$ 0.85",
            "b": "$ 1.98",
            "c": "$ 2.54",
            "d": "$ 3.55"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "Use Put-Call parity: S + P = PV(K) + C, and rearrange for C = S + P – PV(K). Then use S = 255, P = 12.34, K = 275 and r = 4.25% to discount and obtain PV(K ) = 263.79. You have then C = $ 3.55."
        },
        {
          "question": "You are an LBO artist. You are thinking of setting up a holding company ALL Co., endowed with 10 mln EUR cash and to buy out company MID Inc., whose total value of assets currently equals 100 mln EUR. MID has 20 mln EUR of outstanding debt and 2 million shares outstanding. Your plan is to borrow the amount of money necessary to make a tender offer for 50% of the shares of MID. In this tender offer, you offer to pay each MID share its current market price (= the market price of the MID share right before the announcement of a tender offer, assuming there is no leakage of information). If your tender offer is successful, you buy exactly the 50% of MID outstanding shares, take control of the company and then merge it with ALL to create a new company, NEW Inc. You will charge the debt which was used to pay the tender offer of MID on the balance sheet of the new company, NEW Inc. Through the restructuring of NEW Inc. you expect to be able to generate 15 mln EUR of extra value on the assets of this new company. The value of one share of NEW after you have taken control of MID, merged it with ALL, and restructured NEW is closest to:",
          "options": {
            "a": "1.5 EUR",
            "b": "25.5 EUR",
            "c": "32.5 EUR",
            "d": "52.5 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "The total value of MID assets before the operation is 100 mln EUR, of which existing debt is worth 20 mln, so total value of equity is 80 mln. Given that there are 2 million shares outstanding, before the LBO the share price of MID is equal to 40 EUR. In order to buy 50% of MID' shares (= 1 million shares) at the market price before the tender offer is announced (40 EUR), you need to borrow 40 mln EUR (you can reach the same result by noticing that you need to pay 50% of 80 mln, the total value of equity of MID). This additional 40 mln EUR debt will be on the balance sheet of the new company NEW you create by merging MID with ALL. Total value of NEW (after restructuring) = 100 mln (from MID) + 10 mln (from ALL) + 15 mln (from restructuring) = 125 mln. Total value of NEW debt = 20 mln (from MID) + 40 mln (necessary for the takeover) = 60 mln. Therefore, total value of NEW equity = 125 – 60 = 65 mln. Share price = 65M/2M = 32.5 EUR (because there are still 2 million shares outstanding)."
        },
        {
          "question": "An entrepreneur wants to develop a new project. The project earns an uncertain payoff in one year, equal to 10 mln EUR in case of success, and equal to 2 mln EUR in case of failure. The probability of success equals 3/4. The entrepreneur earns 0.5 mln EUR from this project in case of success, while (s)he knows that (s)he will earn zero from the project in case of failure. The entrepreneur has no funds to invest in the project, and asks some external, risk-neutral investors to finance this project. Suppose the interest rate that these investors can earn on the financial market by financing projects with analogous characteristics is 12.5% What is the maximum amount risk-neutral investors are willing to invest in this project?",
          "options": {
            "a": "6.78 mln EUR",
            "b": "7.02 mln EUR",
            "c": "7.625 mln EUR",
            "d": "7.785 mln EUR"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "The income that the entrepreneur can offer to risk-neutral, outside investors, if they accept to invest in this project is, at most, equal to (3/4)*(10-0.5) + (1/4)*2 = 7.625 mln EUR. Risk-neutral investors want to earn (at least) 12.5% on this investment, and therefore are willing to invest 7.625 mln EUR/1.125 = 6.77777 mln EUR (at most)."
        },
        {
          "question": "The price of a given stock today is 35.75 EUR. There is a call option on this stock expiring in one year, with strike price 32 EUR. According to the average market's expectations, the price of the stock in one year, at the call expiration date, is going to be either 38.95 EUR or 30.25 EUR. The risk-free rate is zero. The price of the call option today is closest to: (Hint: to price the call, use the replicating portfolio method)",
          "options": {
            "a": "1.12 EUR",
            "b": "2.75 EUR",
            "c": "3.24 EUR",
            "d": "4.40 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "The call option payoff at expiration is equal to: 38.95 – 32 = 6.95 if the stock price in one year (at expiration of the call) is going to be 38.95; 0 if the stock price is going to be 30.25 < 32, the strike price (you will not exercise the call at expiration). Construct then the replicating portfolio: 38.95 * Δ + B = 6.95; 30.25 * Δ + B = 0. The solution is Δ = 0.7988 and B= - 24.165. The price of the call today is C = 35.75 * Δ + B = 4.3921."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "date": "June 22nd, 2022",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Suppose we are living in a Modigliani-Miller world with frictionless capital markets. Suppose a firm invests in a new project that costs I mln EUR and has a negative NPV (there are some agency problems in the company, and this explains why a negative-NPV project is undertaken). Suppose the firm has no debt in its capital structure, and the new investment is entirely financed with new equity. Because of this investment, the market value of the firm total assets:",
          "options": {
            "a": "increases by I mln EUR",
            "b": "decreases by I mln EUR",
            "c": "increases by less than I mln EUR",
            "d": "increases by more than I mln EUR"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "Consider the market-value Balance Sheet: the total value of assets increases by the investment cost I plus the PV of expected future cash-flows generated by the investment, i.e. its NPV. Being NPV < 0, the total value of assets increases by less than I."
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose we are living in a Modigliani-Miller world with frictionless capital markets. As in the previous question, a firm invests in a new project that costs I mln EUR and has a negative NPV. Therefore, in the answers below, NPV is a negative number (in mln EUR). This is the first and only investment of the firm, which did not exist before. This investment is financed half with new debt and half with new equity. The new debt issued to finance 50% of I is riskless and the risk-free interest rate is zero. Because of the investment in this new project, the market value of the new equity is (in mln EUR):",
          "options": {
            "a": "more than 0.5*I",
            "b": "equal to (0.5*I + NPV)",
            "c": "equal to 0.5*I",
            "d": "lower than (0.5*I + NPV)"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "Again considering the market-value Balance Sheet, one sees that the total value of assets increases by I + NPV < I, given that NPV < 0. Given that the investment I has been financed by equity and debt both at 50%, the new debt is riskless, and the riskless interest rate is zero, the value of new debt equals its face value, i.e. 0.5*I. Therefore, the value of new equity is exactly (0.5*I + NPV) mln EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of the following can be considered as indirect costs of bankruptcy?",
          "options": {
            "a": "The destruction of human capital specific to the firm' technology",
            "b": "Reorganization plans",
            "c": "Legal and administrative costs related to firm liquidation",
            "d": "Costs suffered by public interventions in order to reorganize the firm"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "All the other costs are direct costs of bankruptcy."
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of the following statements about the \"Asset Substitution” effect is true? (only one statement is true):",
          "options": {
            "a": "It gives shareholders the incentive to pay out excessive dividends",
            "b": "It is possible only if the debt in the capital structure of the firm is riskless",
            "c": "It gives shareholders incentives to replace low-risk assets with high-risk ones",
            "d": "It can lead to overinvestment if the high-risk assets have a positive NPV"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "There can be “asset substitution” only if the debt is risky: with riskless debt in the capital structure the incentives to invest for shareholders are unchanged when the level of debt changes, so b. is wrong. Also, managers do not have incentives to pay larger dividends when leverage is high, because this puts the firm at risk of lacking liquidity, so a. is wrong. If the high-risk assets which are selected due to the high level of debt are positive-NPV assets, we do not have overinvestment, but efficient investment, so d. is wrong."
        },
        {
          "question": "All other things being equal, firms with lower growth opportunities operating in countries with high corporate tax rate should better:",
          "options": {
            "a": "retain cash rather than pay it out",
            "b": "they should be indifferent between retaining cash and paying it out",
            "c": "they should invest also in negative-NPV projects",
            "d": "pay out cash rather than retain it"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "One of the benefits of retaining cash is to be able to finance growth opportunities, while one of its costs is to have to pay corporate taxes (on retained earnings, for example). Therefore, if there are low growth opportunities and high corporate taxes, shareholders are better off if cash is paid out, coeteris paribus."
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose that managers of a corporation know more about the future earnings' prospects of the firm than the investors operating on the market. Then it is believed that the decision of paying out dividends by managers signals some information to the market. Which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "To increase dividend signals that the management knows that the firm has plenty of investment opportunities to undertake",
            "b": "To increase dividend conveys the same signal as repurchasing firm shares",
            "c": "To decrease dividend signals that the management has given up hope that earnings will rebound in the near term and so needs to reduce the dividend to save cash",
            "d": "None of the above is true."
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "a is wrong because the management usually increases dividends if they believe they do not have interesting investment opportunities in the near future. B is wrong because share repurchases do not contain a commitment element, given that they are occasional events. D is wrong because c is true."
        },
        {
          "question": "Consider an investor who is short of one put option, and who does not own the underlying stock. Looking only at this investor' payoff at the expiration date of the option, which of the following statements is true? (Only one statement is true)",
          "options": {
            "a": "The investor' loss decreases in the price of the stock at expiration",
            "b": "The investor' loss increases in the price of the stock at expiration",
            "c": "The investor' loss can be higher than the strike price of the option",
            "d": "The investor' loss is zero if the price of the stock at expiration is lower than the strike of the put option"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "See the graph in the slide “short position in a put at expiration”."
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose you want to buy one call option on Stellantis stock. Both options expire exactly in one year. The strike price of each option is 13 EUR, and the current price per-share of Stellantis is 12.30 EUR. The risk-free rate is 2% and the price of a put is 1.58 EUR. Using the put-call parity, what should be the price of a call?",
          "options": {
            "a": "0.58 EUR",
            "b": "0.98 EUR",
            "c": "1.02 EUR",
            "d": "1.13 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "Use Put-Call parity: S + P = PV(K) + C, and rearrange for C = S + P – PV(K). Then use S = 12.30, P = 1.58, K = 13 and r = 2% to discount and obtain PV(K ) = 12.75. You have then C = 1.13 EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "Two European call options with a strike price of 5 EUR are written on two different stocks. Both call options expire exactly in one month from now. Suppose that at expiration, the low-volatility stock will be worth either 4 EUR or 6 EUR, with each price having equal probability. The high-volatility stock will be worth either 7.5 EUR EUR or 2.5 EUR EUR, with each price having equal probability. Assuming that investors on the financial markets are risk-neutral and that the risk-free interest rate equals zero, what is the price of the two options today?",
          "options": {
            "a": "Price of the option on low-volatility stock = 0.25; price of the option on high-volatility stock = 2.5 EUR",
            "b": "Price of the option on low-volatility stock = 0.5; price of the option on high-volatility stock = 1.25 EUR",
            "c": "Price of the option on low-volatility stock = 0.5; price of the option on high-volatility stock = 2 EUR",
            "d": "Price of the option on low-volatility stock = 0.25; price of the option on high-volatility stock = 1.25 EUR"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "Given that the investors are risk-neutral and that the risk-free rate equals zero, the price of each call option today is simply the present value of the expected payoff at expiration. For the low volatility stock the payoff at expiration equals (6 – 5) = 1 EUR, with probability ½, so that its expected payoff is 0.5 EUR. For the high-volatility stock the payoff at expiration is (7.5 – 5) = 2.5 EUR, with probability ½, so that its expected payoff is 1.25 EUR."
        },
        {
          "question": "One of the key ideas of “prospect theory” is that:",
          "options": {
            "a": "Low probabilities events are underweighted, moderate and high probabilities events are overweighted",
            "b": "When taking decisions, individuals consider the “utility\" of absolute outcomes",
            "c": "When taking decisions, individuals consider the positive or negative deviations from a reference point",
            "d": "None of the above"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "See slide 10, Behavioral corporate finance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of the following behavioral biases are less plausible to affect the decision of the management of a firm to acquire another company?",
          "options": {
            "a": "The way different acts are framed may influence an individual's choice",
            "b": "Being overoptimistic about the future synergy with the acquired company",
            "c": "Being overconfident",
            "d": "Neglecting the possible winner's curse"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "Framing of acts may matter for many individual decisions, but it is unlikely to matter for the decision to acquire a company, contrarily to the other biases, which have been largely observed."
        },
        {
          "question": "In order to evaluate real options we use the same methods as with financial options, with two additional assumptions:",
          "options": {
            "a": "As underlying security we use a share of the firm who plans to invest in the project, and we assume there are no arbitrage opportunities",
            "b": "As underlying security we use the project itself, and we assume there are no arbitrage opportunities",
            "c": "As underlying security we use the financial option that describes best the real option related to the project we want to invest in, and we assume there are arbitrage opportunities",
            "d": "None of the above"
          },
          "answer": "b",
          "solution": "See slide 19 in the lecture on Real Option Approach"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of the following can be considered as an effect of the introduction of “limited liability\" of shareholders in modern corporation?",
          "options": {
            "a": "The emergence of commercial banks",
            "b": "The emergence of block-holders in the ownership structure of firms",
            "c": "The distinction between shareholders and stakeholders of companies",
            "d": "The ability for shareholders to diversify risk"
          },
          "answer": "d",
          "solution": "When investors started being protected by limited liability as shareholders (=owners) of companies, they started investing lower amounts in many different companies, which allowed them to diversify risk. Notice that this would be very risky if shareholders-owners where fully liable of corporation's debts."
        },
        {
          "question": "Your company is planning to invest in a new project. The investment required equals 500 (all numbers are in thousands EUR). You can invest 50 in this project of your own money, while you plan to raise the missing 450 from some risk-neutral, outside investors, in the form of new equity. There are two versions of this new project. One, version “L”, is very similar to a project that you undertook previously. Another one, version \"H\", is extremely innovative. Both versions provide an uncertain return in one year: if the project is successful, both versions earn 800; if the project is not successful, they both earn 200. The probability of “H” being successful is ¼ while the probability of “L” being successful is 1/4. You prefer to develop version “L” since this requires less effort. Therefore, if you develop version “L”, you enjoy private benefits B (in monetary terms, again in thousands EUR), while you obtain zero private benefits if you develop version \"H\". What is the maximum level of private benefits B (in thousands EUR) such that the Incentive Compatibility constraint which ensures you will develop version “H” is satisfied? What is the maximum income you can credibly pledge to the external investors (“pledgeable income\") if the level of B is such that you can credibly convince them you will develop version \"H\"?",
          "options": {
            "a": "B lower or equal than 30 (thousand) EUR; maximum pledgeable income equal to 585 (thousand) EUR",
            "b": "B lower or equal than 7 (thousand) EUR; maximum pledgeable income equal to 100 (thousand) EUR",
            "c": "B lower or equal than 25 (thousand) EUR; maximum pledgeable income equal to 500 (thousand) EUR",
            "d": "B lower or equal than 35 (thousand) EUR; maximum pledgeable income equal to 650 (thousand) EUR"
          },
          "answer": "a",
          "solution": "Given that you can finance 50 over 500 of the new investment, you have the right to 10% of the future payoffs. Write the IC-constraint considering that if you implement version “H” the probability of success is 3/4 (and failure 1/4) but you do not obtain B, while if you implement version “L” the probability of success is 1/4 (and failure 3/4) and you obtain B: 0.1 * (3/4 * 800 + 1/4 * 200) >= 0.1 * (1/4 * 800 + 3/4 * 200) + B which is satisfied if B <= 30. In such a case, you can credibly convince the outside investors that you will select version “H”, and they correctly anticipate to earn: 0.9 * (3/4 * 800 + 1/4 * 200) = 585 which is then the maximum income you can pledge to pay them."
        },
        {
          "question": "Under which assumption \"free-riding\" behavior of existing shareholders of a target company could make impossible for a bidder to earn a positive profit by taking over the company?",
          "options": {
            "a": "The existing shareholders consider that the probability with which the bidder's offer for the firm is going to be successful depends on their individual decision whether to sell or not their share",
            "b": "The existing shareholders do not know exactly the value of each target company share after the takeover",
            "c": "The existing shareholders consider that the probability with which the bidder's offer for the firm is going to be successful does not depend on their individual decision whether to sell or not their share",
            "d": "None of the above"
          },
          "answer": "c",
          "solution": "We have seen that b is wrong: even if the target shareholders do not know exactly the post-takeover value v_1, but if they are rational and they anticipate the acquirer behaves rationally, still they will not tender (sell) their share, if they believe the takeover outcome does not depend on their decision to tender or not. A is also not correct, because if they think they can influence the outcome of the tender offer, then the probability of success depends on their choice, and it is possible that they are forced to tender their shares for an offered price p lower than v_1."
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}
